# Ao LIU

# Ph.D. in Computer Science



# Summary

Research Machine Learning (Recommendation Systems, Learning to Rank, Algorithm Design, etc.),
Interests Differential Privacy, Computational Social Choice, and Quantum Computation

**Experience** 1+ years of industry experience in personalization, recommendation systems, LLM, theoretical computer science, differential privacy, and adversarial robustness

**Academia** Published 20+ papers and received 250+ citations to date. Reviewed 50+ papers for top AI conferences or journals.

#### Education

01/2018 – 05/2023 **Ph.D. in Computer Science**, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute (RPI) Troy, NY Thesis: *Group Decision Makings from Partial Preferences* [Link]

08/2015 – 05/2018 M.Eng. in Material Engineering, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute (RPI) Troy, NY Focus on optics and polymer physics, received Presidential Graduate Research Fellowship

08/2010 – 05/2014 **B.S. in Mathematics and Physics**, Tsinghua University Beijing, China *Minor in Computer Technology*, and *in Academic Talent Program* 

### Experience

07/2023 – Present Research Software Engineer at Google Core ML Mountain View, CA
Design and Research More Efficient Transformers for Recommendation Systems

05/2022 - 08/2022 Research Intern at Google Core ML Mountain View, CA

Project: A More Accurate Position Bias Estimator for Unbiased Learning to Rank

- $\circ$  Significant prediction accuracy improvement ( $\sim$ 8%) v.s. state-of-the-art without any cost
  - Proposed a novel probabilistic model to more accurately estimate position bias and designed an unbiased recommendation system based on it.
  - Implemented the data pipeline and machine learning algorithm for the proposed unbiased recommendation system. Integrated all into Google codebase. (Python, TensorFlow, C/C++)

08/2018 – 12/2018 Visiting Scholar at MIT-IBM Watson AI Lab and Project: Certifiably Robust Interpretation via Rényi Cambridge, MA

Project: Certifiably Robust Interpretation via Rényi Differential Privacy

- 05/2019 08/2019  $\odot$  Significant robustness improvement ( $\sim 12\%$ ) plus accuracy improvement v.s. state-of-the-art
  - Yes! We improved both robustness and accuracy, which usually are trade-offs in machine learning.
  - Designed the first algorithm in the world with theoretically guaranteed top-k robustness against  $\ell_{\infty}$ -norm attacks, where the theoretical proofs relies on Rényi differential privacy.
  - Implemented the proposed algorithm and tested its robustness, accuracy, and computational efficiency on image classification and objective detection. (*PyTorch, TorchRay, TensorFlow*)
  - O Delivered one academic paper (on top AI journal and conference) and two patents.

#### Skills

Implementation Programming languages: Python, C/C++, Matlab

Tools and platforms: TensorFlow, PyTorch, TorchRay, LATEX

**Design/ Theory** Algorithm design, Statistics, Time/Sample-complexity analysis, User-modeling, Markov chain Mount-Carlo, Privacy analysis, Robustness analysis, Model identifiability, Smoothed analysis

## Review Services

Journal Information Sciences, TMLR, ACM ToIS, Sankhya B

Conference NeurIPS (20,21,22&23), ICML (22,23&24), ICLR (23&24), AAAI (21&22), IJCAI-22

TMLR	Smoothed Differential Privacy [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Yu-Xiang Wang, and Lirong Xia
UAI-23	Accelerating Voting by Quantum Computation [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Qishen Han, Lirong Xia, and Nengkun Yu
	Certifiably Robust Interpretation via Rényi Differential Privacy [Link] [ArXiv] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Xiaoyu Chen, Sijia Liu, Lirong Xia, and Chuang Gan
AAAI-22	The Semi-Random Likelihood of Doctrinal Paradoxes [PDF] $\underline{Ao\ Liu}$ and Lirong Xia
UAI-20 (oral)	How Private Are Commonly-Used Voting Rules? [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Yun Lu, Lirong Xia, and Vassilis Zikas
AAAI-19 (oral)	Near-Neighbor Methods in Random Preference Completion [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Qiong Wu, Zhenming Liu, and Lirong Xia
AAAI-19 (oral)	Learning Plackett-Luce Mixture from Partial Preferences [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Zhibing Zhao, Chao Liao, Pinyan Lu, and Lirong Xia
ETRA-19  (oral)	Differential Privacy for Eye-Tracking Data [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Lirong Xia, Andrew Duchowski, Reynold Bailey, Kenneth Holmqvist, and Eakta Jain
US Patent	Certifiably Robust Interpretation [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Sijia Liu, Bo Wu, Lirong Xia, Qi Cheng Li, and Chuang Gan
US Patent	Interpretation Maps with Guaranteed Robustness [PDF] <u>Ao Liu</u> , Sijia Liu, Abhishek Bhandwaldar, Chuang Gan, Lirong Xia, and Qi Cheng Li
AAAI-23 (oral)	Differentially Private Condorcet Voting [PDF] Zhechen Li, <u>Ao Liu</u> , Lirong Xia, Yongzhi Cao, and Hanpin Wang
IJCAI-22 (oral)	Learning Mixtures of Random Utility Models with Features from Incomplete Preferences Zhibing Zhao, <u>Ao Liu</u> , and Lirong Xia [PDF]
	Learning to Design Fair and Private Voting Rules [PDF] Farhad Mohsin, <u>Ao Liu</u> , Pin-Yu Chen, Francesca Rossi, and Lirong Xia
ETRA-20 Adjunct	Let It Snow: Adding Pixel Noise to Protect the Users Identity [Link] Brendan John, <u>Ao Liu</u> , Lirong Xia, Sanjeev Koppal, and Eakta Jain
•	Simulation of Pulse Responses of Lithium Salt-Doped Poly-Ethyleneoxide [Link <u>Ao Liu</u> , F. Zeng, Y. Hu, S. Lu, W. Dong, X. Li, C. Chang, and D. Guo
	Controlling Ion Conductance and Channels to Achieve Synaptic-like Frequency Selectivity Siheng Lu, Fei Zeng, Wenshuai Dong, <u>Ao Liu</u> , Xiaojun Li, and Jingting Luo [Link]
	Awards and Teaching
09/2019 - 05/2022	RPI-IBM AI Horizon Scholarship
09/2016 - 05/2017	RPI Presidential Graduate Research Fellowship [Certificate]
01/2023 - 05/2023	Teaching Assistant of CSCI 4150: Introduction to AI

Selected Publication

08/2017 - 12/2017 Teaching Assistant of MATH 1020: Calculus II

04/2021 Guest Lecture at CSCI 4967/6967: Economics and Computation